

Maximilian Bernkopf

MATH GEEK + DATA NERD

maximilianbernkopf.github.io/esa/

MaximilianBernkopf

maximilianbernkopf

Coogle Scholar

Summary_

Max is pursuing his PhD in computational mathematics at the TU Wien focussing on the numerics of time-harmonic wave propagation problems. Besides mathematics, he is a true data nerd. He loves handling and visualizing big data sets and discovering the unique stories they can tell. His languages of choice are R and Python, depending on the task at hand. He gained his data science experience working at start-ups in Vienna, where he solved problems involving time series analysis and outlier detection.

Education

PhD Candidate in Computational Mathematics

Vienna, Austria
09/2017-current

TU WIEN

- Doctoral thesis: "Finite Element Analysis of the Heterogeneous Helmholtz Equation and Least Squares Methods"
- Supervisor: Prof. Jens Markus Melenk, PhD

Dipl.-Ing. (equivalent MSc) in Financial and Actuarial Mathematics

Vienna, Austria 11/2015-06/2016

TU WIEN

- Master thesis: "Analysis of the alpha-hypergeometric stochastic volatility model"
- · Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Stefan Gerhold

BSc in Financial and Actuarial Mathematics

Vienna, Austria

TU WIEN

07/2011 11/2010

Matura (High school graduation equivalent)

Vienna, Austria

SCHOTTENGYMNASIUM

10/2002-06/2010

Work Experience _____

Data ScientistVienna, Austria

INTRABASE

09/2016-09/2017

- Focus on statistical learning and outlier detection.
- Development of statistical algorithms for unsupervised outlier detection.
- High dimensional anomaly detection of categorical and numerical data.

Data ScientistVienna, Austria

MANTIGMA

08/2016-09/2017

- Focus on time series analysis and supervised learning.
- · Account balance forecasting for retail banking.
- Electricity demand forecasting utilizing classical mathematical time series models as well as novel deep learning techniques.
- Machine learning based credit scoring models.

Research Assistant Vienna, Austria

TU WIEN, RESEARCH UNIT OF FINANCIAL AND ACTUARIAL MATHEMATICS

10/2015-06/2016

· Focus on credit risk models and their implementation.

Vienna, Austria

Internship

09/2013-12/2013

• Focus on Solvency II.

FMA FINANZMARKTAUFSICHT ÖSTERREICH

Community Service / Paramedic

Vienna, Austria

Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund

12/2010-08/2011



R tidyverse (dplyr, ggplot2, tibble, purrr, readr etc.), dbplyr, data.table, shiny,

forecast, caret, tidymodels, plotly, rmarkdown

Python ngsolve, numpy, pandas, matplotlib, scipy, sklearn

Proficient in Matlab, Mapel, Mathematica, LaTex, git

Basic Knowledge of SQL, Hugo, C, C++, Java

Languages German (native), English (fluent), Russian (basic)

Operating System of Choice Linux + i3wm

Hobbies and Random Bits

Sports Calisthenics, Climbing, Bouldering, Gymnastics & Acrobatics

Non-athletic Hobbies Dancing, Reading stoic philosophy, Non-modern Art, Listening to audiobooks at 2x the speed

Less Usefull Skills Juggeling, Yoyo-tricks, Solving the Rubiks cube **Guilty Pleasures** Selfimporvement books, Reddit, Memes, Cheese

Random Facts Can fit at least three Soletti sideways in his mouth, Dyed his hair blond to be Son Goku for Halloween,

Google Local Guide Level 7, Weirdly enthusiastic about his Dyson

Teaching

Tutor - Analysis 1-3, Computer Mathematics

TU WIEN, INSTITUTE OF ANALYSIS AND SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING

Seminar Instructor - Seminar on inverse problems

TU WIEN, INSTITUTE OF ANALYSIS AND SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING

Seminar Instructor - Seminar on uncertainty quantification and approximation theory of neural networks

TU WIEN, INSTITUTE OF ANALYSIS AND SCIENTIFIC COMPUTING

Vienna, Austria

2015-2021 Vienna, Austria

03/2019-07/2019

Vienna, Austria

10/2018-02/2019

Research Stays _____

Université Polytechnique Hauts-de-France

WORKING WITH PROF. DR. SERGE NICAISE

Universität Zürich

WORKING WITH PROF. DR. STEFAN SAUTER

Valenciennes, France

09/2020-12/2020

Zürich, Switzerland

09/2019-12/2019

Publications

[5] Wavenumber-explicit stability and convergence analysis of hp Finite Element discretizations of Helmholtz problems in piecewise smooth media, in preparation

M. Bernkopf, T. Chaumont-Frelet, J. M. Melenk

[4] Optimal convergence rates in L^2 for a first order system least squares finite element method. Part II: inhomogeneous boundary conditions, in preparation

M. Bernkopf, J. M. Melenk

[3] Solvability of Discrete Helmholtz Equations, submitted

M. Bernkopf, S. Sauter, C. Torres, A. Veit

arXiv e-prints arXiv:2105.02273, 2021

[2] Optimal convergence rates in L^2 for a first order system least squares finite element method. Part I: homogeneous boundary conditions, submitted

M. Bernkopf, J. M. Melenk

arXiv e-prints arXiv:2012.12919, 2020

[1] Analysis of the hp-Version of a First Order System Least Squares Method for the Helmholtz Equation M. Bernkopf, J. M. Melenk

Advanced Finite Element Methods with Applications: Selected Papers from the 30th Chemnitz Finite Element Symposium 2017, 2019